Guide to the Imperial Portrait Photograph File [1856-1870] PR 210
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV: Portraits by Jeremiah Gurney
  The group portrait of the Parmly and Ward families came to the Society with a family legend attached. The subjects of the photograph are the friends and family of Julia Parmly (1835-1914) who married lawyer Frederick Billings (1823-1890) in New York on March 31, 1862. Present in the picture are Julia's father, the prominent New York dentist (known as "the father of American dentistry") Dr. Eleazer Parmly (1797-1874), Julia's brother Erick Parmly (1829-1907) and sisters Anna Parmly (incorrectly identified in the inscription as Louisa, who died in 1845) and Mary Parmly Ward (1831-1914), Mary's husband Charles H. Ward (1833-1905), and Charles' mother Abby Hall Ward and brother John Ward (1838-1896). Also present are family friends Gilman Morton and Benjamin Church. The Wards shown in this photograph were the mother and brothers of William Greene Ward. According to a twentieth-century inscription on the verso of the photograph's mount, the group had their picture taken just after they had escorted Julia and Frederick Billings to a dock to board a ship taking them on their wedding trip to California. Robin Winks, in his biography Frederick Billings: A Life (New York: Oxford University Press, 1991), states the chronology thus: the couple took a wedding trip to Philadelphia, then returned to New York to pack, and on April 11, "sailed for California on the Northern Light, seen off by a tiny band of family and friends." Prior to meeting Julia Parmly in New York and immediately marrying her, Billings was a resident of San Francisco, and the couple traveled there to close out his businesses. The Billings then returned to New York and settled here.
  Jeremiah Gurney (1812-1895) was one of New York's finest portrait photographers, and is known primarily for his daguerrean work. His carte de visite and cabinet-format portraits are not uncommon in public and private collections, but his Imperial format portraits are rare. Emily Ward's portrait measures 19 by 16-1/4 inches and is on its original studio mount marked by Gurney in two places: an oval blind stamp in the front lower margin and a paper label on the verso; both give the studio's address as 707 Broadway, the location of Gurney's studio from 1858 through 1868. The group portrait is not marked, but is attributed to Gurney based on the quality of the photograph, and on the distinctive carpet showing in the image, which is also seen in marked Gurney carte de visite photographs (for examples, see album no. 415 in PR 002, the Album File, The House of Bishops of the Protestant Episcopal Church of the United States Photographed from life during the Triennial Convention by J. Gurney & Son (New York: T. Porter Shaw, 1862.) The family inscription on the verso of the mount suggests the photographer was William Kurtz (1834-1904), but he is not listed in the New York City directories until 1865.
  - Parmly and Ward family members, [1862 Apr. 11] (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
    salted paper photograph, 13 x 14 3/4 in.
  - Ward, Emily (ca. 1832-1877), [1858] (Box Unknown container 688 for instance of Ward, Emily (ca. 1832-1877), Folder unknown container)
    salted paper photograph, 19 x 16 1/4 in.
- Series V: Portraits by Unidentified Photographers
  Series V. Portraits by Unidentified Photographers contains three portraits, two of which are identified men. They are Colonel John Jacob Astor III (1822-1890) and William Pitt Fessenden (1806-1869); both may be later enlargements from negatives made in the mid-1860s but are included in this collection based on their sheet size and vintage. The third portrait is of an unidentified man with an American flag, and features drapery and a classical column often seen in Mathew Brady portraits. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by sitter.
  - Astor III, John Jacob, Colonel (1822-1890), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    albumen photograph, 18 3/8 x 14 3/4 in.
  - Fessenden, William Pitt (1806-1869), undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    albumen photograph, 20 1/4 x 15 in.
  - Unidentified man with American flag, undated (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    salted paper photograph, 18 3/8 x 14 3/4 in.
- Oversize Material
  Oversize material is filed in one flat folder housed in a map case drawer.
  - From Series I. Portraits by Mathew Brady
    - Scott, Winfield (1786-1866), undated (Folder 28)
  - From Series III. Portrait by Charles Fredricks
    - Webb, James Watson (1802-1884), 1858 (Folder 28)
  - From Series IV. Portraits by Jeremiah Gurney
    - Ward, Emily (ca. 1837-1877), [1858] (Folder 28)